Have you ever wondered
if there’s a natural way
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Back by popular demand,
it’s the NutritionFacts Grab Bag,
where we look at the latest science
on a whole variety of topics.
And we start with a story on the FDA-
approved bioidentical hormones
that skirt the standardization concerns
of compounded preparations.
The news that
menopausal hormone therapy
had the potential to cause
higher rates of breast cancer,
cardiovascular disease,
and overall harm
rocked women and physicians
across the country.
The study arm used progesterone
and Premarin,
because it was the most commonly
prescribed form of estrogen
and is still prescribed
more than a million times
a year in the U.S.
It's a mixture of more
than 50 different estrogens
from horse pee.
("Premarin" comes from the words
"pregnant mare urine,"
if you're skeptical,
try crushing a pill
and sniffing it.)
The dour findings
of the Women's Health Initiative
(combined with some high-profile
celebrity endorsements)
saw interest shift
to "bioidentical hormones,"
made from plants
rather than a horse source.
They are marketed as being safer
and more effective.
No wonder estimates
peg the annual number
of prescriptions
at 30 million a year,
constituting
a billion-dollar industry.
One reason patients may believe
compounded hormone therapy
is safer is that,
thanks to a legal loophole,
they are not mandated
to provide
the FDA insert required
for commercial products
warning about side effects.
Purchased at regular pharmacies,
hormones have
a prominent black box
with an all-caps
"WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER,
CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS,
BREAST CANCER,
AND PROBABLE DEMENTIA."
There's no evidence
that bioidentical hormones
are any safer,
but the missing laundry list
of side effects
may give patients
a false sense of security.
Another appeal
is customized dosing
based on saliva hormone testing,
but such tests are considered
to be unreliable
and so recommended against,
since the only people
who profit
are the ones
trying to sell you the tests.
Custom-compounded hormones
are not FDA-approved,
have not been shown to be safer
or more effective,
and may lack standardization
of quality, purity, and dose.
When the FDA
or muckraking journalists
have filled
the same prescriptions
in compounding pharmacies
in different states,
a third of the stated
estrogen contents
were off
by as much as 250 percent.
No wonder all the major
American medical societies
that counsel physicians
on treating menopausal women
recommend against
compounded hormones,
including the American College
of Obstetrics and Gynecology,
the Endocrine Society,
and the North American
Menopause Society.
Characterizing the pushback
they got from their 2020 review
recommending against the use
of bioidentical hormones,
the National Academies
of Sciences,
Engineering,
and Medicine concluded,
"It is clear
from these communications
that many clinicians,
compounding pharmacists,
and patients hold minimum,
if any,
concerns regarding
the medication's safety
and effectiveness."
Now, as of 2019,
there are pee-free FDA-approved
bioidentical hormones
that skirt
the standardization concerns
of compounded preparations,
but that just brings us back
to square one,
since they are considered
to have
the same risk/benefit profile.
The multibillion-dollar
compounded hormone industry
is considered a "leading source
of disinformation,"
but the same could be said
of Big Pharma.
With so many billions of dollars
at stake,
it's hard to know
who to trust.
When in doubt,
I turn to The Medical Letter
on Drugs and Therapeutics,
considered one
of the least biased sources
in medicine.
It's kind of like
the Consumer Reports
of the drug world,
and, in fact,
was actually co-founded
by the co-founder
of the publisher
of Consumer Reports
more than 50 years ago.
As The Medical Letter
used to brag on their website,
it "does not accept grants,
from any source;
donations, from anyone;
[or] funding, from any entity."
They won't let their work be
used for promotional purposes,
and they don't accept
any advertising.
In their review of the evidence,
they concluded,
"There is no acceptable evidence
that bio-identical hormones
are safer."
So, how do you treat
menopausal symptoms
like hot flashes?
The American College of
Obstetricians and Gynecologists
suggests palliative measures,
such as "consuming cool drinks,"
but is there really no way
to treat hot flashes
without the cancer, clots,
and coronaries?
Thankfully there is,
as I cover in a video series
that starts with
Menopausal Hot Flashes
Are Not Inevitable
and then moves
from prevention to treatment.
In our next story,
we look at how laser
therapy is marketed
as a promising alternative
to drugs and scalpels
for treating hair loss.
But does it work?
In my book, How Not to Age,
I discuss all the drugs,
foods, supplements,
and surgeries that can treat
age-related hair loss,
but what about non-dietary,
non-drug,
non-surgical interventions?
Autologous platelet-rich plasma,
where concentrated portions
of your own blood
is repeatedly injected
into your scalp,
appears to have an efficacy
similar to the available drugs,
though the available evidence
is considered insufficient
to recommend it,
and so remains unapproved
in the U.S. or Europe
for hair restoration purposes.
Scalp Botox
is also not recommended.
The thought was
that relaxing scalp muscles
might improve blood flow,
but when actually put
to the test
actually caused hair loss
in some pilot study
participants.
Then, there are lasers.
In the 1960s,
a Hungarian physician
published the paper,
"The effect of laser beams
on the growth of hair in mice,"
detailing
a serendipitous discovery
that a low-powered ruby laser
increased the hair growth
on the shaved backs of mice.
The mechanism appears to be
increased blood flow.
The floodgates opened
when the FDA cleared
the first low-level
laser therapy device
for age-related
pattern hair loss in 2007,
and now, there are clinics
advertising lasers
for everything
from tennis elbow
to "scrotal rejuvenation."
There have been at least ten
randomized, controlled trials
of low-level
laser therapy devices
for hair loss, and the efficacy
has been found comparable
or even superior to the drugs.
They are noninvasive and appear
to be relatively safe.
Mild side effects
include itching, acne,
and scalp tenderness
that usually resolves
within two weeks.
Reviews typically conclude
that laser therapy
may be a promising alternative
to drugs and scalpels,
but there remains
considerable skepticism
within the dermatology community
and for good reason.
Most of the laser therapy trials
were funded
by the manufacturers
of the tested products
themselves.
This is true of hair loss
treatments across the board,
but laser studies appear
particularly reticent
to provide visual evidence
or inquire
about perhaps the most important
outcome of all,
patient satisfaction.
When the first independent study
was performed,
blinded evaluations
of before-and-after photographs
could not detect a difference
in hair density or caliber.
In two studies that compared
subjective satisfaction
between laser
and sham placebo devices,
no significant difference
could be found either.
In other words,
from the patient's perspective,
they just plain don't work.
So, while there are
statistically significant
improvements
in hair density and thickness,
there may be little clinically
significant improvement.
If you want to give them
a try anyway,
there are at least 29
FDA-cleared devices
currently on the market.
There have been no head-to-head
studies between them,
but based on measured outcomes,
there appear to be
no difference
between the comb-style
and hat-style devices,
though those containing
laser diodes exclusively
may have an edge over devices
that include a mix
of both laser diodes and LED.
Do not look into the light,
as prolonged retinal exposure
could be damaging.
Thankfully,
at least most cap designs
have a built-in safety shut-off
to avoid accidental
eye exposure.
Otherwise,
besides general safety caveats
about using
electrical contraptions
in or around water,
such devices are
considered safe,
though they are contraindicated
for those with cancer
of the scalp
due to the potential
for stimulatory effects.
Finally today,
we hear about astralagus root,
one of the most popular herbs
in traditional Chinese medicine
that is marketed as
a “life-prolonging” tonic.
In 2008, it was reported
that a screening
of traditional
Chinese medicine plants
identified a compound
called cycloastragenol
in the roots
of the astragalus plant
that appeared
to moderately enhance
telomerase activation.
That's an enzyme
I've covered before
that our body uses
to try to reverse one aspect
of cellular aging
by elongating your telomeres,
the protective caps
on your chromosomes.
Three years later,
after it was shown
to elongate short telomeres
and improve healthspan
(though not lifespan) in mice,
a one-year human trial
was published.
Although in most of the subjects
telomeres continued
to shorten on average,
there did seem to be
a significant reduction
in the proportion of cells
with critically short telomeres.
And the side effects
looked good,
including a drop
in LDL cholesterol
and blood pressure.
But there was no control group
and cycloastragenol
(branded as "TA-65")
was but one
of over fifty vitamins,
minerals, herbs,
and other compounds they gave
to the research subjects
that year.
When TA-65 was finally
properly put to the test
in randomized controlled trials,
there was no cholesterol
or blood pressure benefit
whatsoever,
but in cytomegalovirus-positive
patients,
a significant
telomere-lengthening effect
was demonstrated at one dose
but not another.
(Those with
chronic viral infections,
such as CMV or HIV,
tend to have white blood cells
with especially truncated
telomeres.)
The only such study
showing clinical benefit
was a year-long pilot study
of TA-65
for early age-related
macular degeneration,
though it was funded
by the company
that sells it
for $600 a bottle.
They grossed
more than $50 million
before the Federal
Trade Commission charged them
with false and deceptive
claims and practices.
That $600
buys you less than a gram
of astragalus root extract.
You can buy
astragalus root extract in bulk
50,000 times cheaper
for less than $20 a pound,
should there ever be
independently verified benefits.
Astragalus root,
well-known as huáng qí in China,
is one of the most popular herbs
in traditional Chinese medicine,
included in hundreds
of herbal formulas
and evidently widely marketed
for millennia
as a "life prolonging" tonic.
No data on that,
but about 30 grams a day
appeared to help
with a type
of autoimmune kidney disease
called idiopathic
membranous nephropathy
in 50 randomized
controlled trials,
but not
placebo-controlled trials;
so, any placebo effects
can't be discounted.
Pregnant or nursing women
are cautioned against
using astragalus,
and a theoretical concern
was raised
that it may activate
a certain oncogene,
a potentially
cancer-causing gene.
However,
dozens of randomized trials
of astragalus-based
herbal preparations
as an add-on therapy
to chemotherapy
for the most common type
of lung cancer
(non-small-cell) found,
if anything,
astragalus to be protective.
Lung cancer is the leading cause
of cancer death in the U.S.
Adding astragalus
to standard platinum-based chemo
reduced the risk of death
as much as 38 percent
at the one-year-mark,
and 25 percent at two years.
However, in almost all trials,
the astragalus was just one
of many herbs used in a formula,
making the effects of astragalus
impossible to tease out,
and unfortunately,
publication bias
is widespread
in the traditional
Chinese medicine literature,
where inconvenient results
may be quietly shelved,
though this in no way
unique to that field.
Similar remarkable results,
with similar critical caveats,
were published for
astragalus-containing formulas
for colorectal cancer,
including
improved quality of life.
Same thing with cervical cancer,
with remarkably reduced
chemotherapy toxicity:
less nausea and vomiting,
less hair loss,
less nerve damage,
and less liver
and kidney toxicity.
Also, less lung damage
from radiation treatments,
and for stomach cancer,
improved quality of life
and quantity of life.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.